<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An act for the more certain and constant supply of the soldiery with pay; and the preventing of any further oppression or damage to the people by free-quarter or billet. Die Sabbathi, 12 Maii, 1649 ... At the Committee of Safety at VVhite-Hall. This committee being acquainted with the great necessities of the armies of this Commonwealth for want of pay, and being desirous, as much as in them lies to prevent the mischiefs and inconveniencies which may fall upon the people of this Commonwealth by free-quarter, wherein great care was taken by the Parliament in the year 1649. upon the like extreme emergencies as are at this present ... The Committee have thought fit to order that the said act of Parliament be reprinted and published ... William Robinson clerk of the Committee of Safety.</title>
            <author>England and Wales.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 29 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A82456</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E1114</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1074_24</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208347</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867304</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867304</idno>
            <idno type="VID">169325</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A82456)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 169325)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 160:E1074[24])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An act for the more certain and constant supply of the soldiery with pay; and the preventing of any further oppression or damage to the people by free-quarter or billet. Die Sabbathi, 12 Maii, 1649 ... At the Committee of Safety at VVhite-Hall. This committee being acquainted with the great necessities of the armies of this Commonwealth for want of pay, and being desirous, as much as in them lies to prevent the mischiefs and inconveniencies which may fall upon the people of this Commonwealth by free-quarter, wherein great care was taken by the Parliament in the year 1649. upon the like extreme emergencies as are at this present ... The Committee have thought fit to order that the said act of Parliament be reprinted and published ... William Robinson clerk of the Committee of Safety.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Committee of Safety.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Henry Hills and John Field, printers to the Committee of Safety,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Ordered to be printed and published November 24, 1659.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "9ber [i.e. November] 28".</note>
                  <note>Title ornament; some text in black letter; initial letter.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Soldiers --  Billeting --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:169325:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ACT FOR The more certain and conſtant Supply of the SOLDIERY with PAY; And the preventing of any further Oppreſsion or Damage to the PEOPLE by Free-quarter or Billet.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license">
                        <p>Die Sabbathi, 12 Maii, 1649.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>ORdered by the Commons aſſembled in Parliament, That this Act be forthwith Printed and Publiſhed.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Hen: Scobell, Cleric. Parliament.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="document">
                        <head>Thurſday the 24<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of Novemb. 1659. <hi>At the Committee of Safety at</hi> VVhite-Hall.</head>
                        <p>THis Committee being acquainted with the great neceſsities of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of this Commonwealth for want of Pay, and being deſirous, as much as in them lies to prevent the Miſchiefs and inconveniencies which may fall upon the People of this Commonwealth by Free-quarter, wherein great care was taken by the Parliament in the year 1649. upon the like extreme Emergencies as are at this preſent, as by the Act of Parliament then made doth appear; The Committee have thought fit to Order that the ſaid Act of Parliament be reprinted and publiſhed, and all Officers Civil and Milita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and all others whom it may concern, are to take notice thereof, and to yield Conformity and due Obedience thereunto, and that the ſame be put into due execution accordingly.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>
                              <hi>WILLIAM ROBINSON</hi> Clerk of the Committee of Safety.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London</hi> Printed by <hi>Henry Hills</hi> and <hi>John Field,</hi> Printers to the Committee of Safety. 1659.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="act">
            <pb facs="tcp:169325:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:169325:2"/>
            <head>AN ACT FOR The more certain and conſtant Supply of the Soldiery with Pay, and the preventing of any further Oppreſsion or Damage to the PEOPLE by Free-quarter or Billet.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Commons aſſembled in Parliament, for the taking off and future avoiding of all Free-quarter, (which the laſt Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers War, and great increaſe of Forces thereby occaſioned, had neceſſarily brought again upon the people) having reſolved again to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band all ſuch Forces as may be ſpared; and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing provided that the reſt (which are yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to be continued) ſhall have conſtant pay aſſigned to them out of the aſſeſſments of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral counties by the Committee for the Army; as alſo an allowance in Money, in lieu of Bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let, ſo as duly receiving the ſame, they may therewith provide and finde themſelves both for Quarter, Billet, and other Neceſſaries, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out further charge or trouble to the people where they lie; And finding that without a preſent ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of Money upon the ſaid aſſeſſments, the Forces cannot be reduced to that proportion
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:169325:3"/>
which the growing Aſſeſſment will ſuffice to pay; and that unleſs the continuing Forces be timely ſupplyed with their pay beforehand, they cannot be enabled or reaſonably required to hold that good order, of maintaining and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding for themſelves (as is intended and Reſolved) without Quarter or Billetting up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the People; Do therefore Enact and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain, and be it Enacted and Ordained by this preſent Parliament, and by authority of the ſame, That the firſt three moneths Aſſeſſment of the ſaid ſix moneths, ſhall be taxed, levied and paid in the ſeveral Counties, to the reſpective Treaſurers or chief Receivers, before the ninth day of <hi>June,</hi> 1649. and that the firſt moneths aſſeſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the latter three moneths, ſhall in like maner be taxed, levied and paid in before the firſt of <hi>July</hi> next following; and the ſecond moneths Aſſeſſment of the ſaid laſt three moneths, before the firſt day of <hi>Auguſt</hi> next enſuing; and the laſt moneth thereof, before the firſt day of <hi>September</hi> next coming; ſo as the aſſignments of pay from the ſaid Committee to the ſeveral Forces, out of the aſſeſſments of the reſpective Counties, may be ſupplyed readily and beforehand, to enable the Soldiery to maintain themſelves, without Free-quarter, Free Billet, or other trouble or charge to the countrey: And the ſeveral Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners for Aſſeſſments, Aſſeſſors and Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectors in the reſpective Counties and places within this Commonwealth, are enjoyned and required, in and according to their ſeveral places and truſts, diligently to ſee to, and take order for the effectual performance hereof, as they tender their own and their countreys eaſe and deliverance from the Burthen and Grievances of Free-quarter, and as they will anſwer the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:169325:3"/>
neglect or failer at their perils. And whereas it often doth, and poſſibly may happen, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the moſt due and careful taxing or levy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the aſſeſſments, that the moneys aſſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon the aſſeſſments, for pay to the ſeveral Forces, may not always be had ſo ſoon, as to come to their hands timely and beforehand, ſo as the Soldiery not having Money ready in hand, cannot in ſuch caſe maintain and provide for themſelves, as is intended, but may be neceſſitated (if they be not otherwiſe ſupplyed with ready money) to take Quarter and Billet upon Credit, till their pay come: And whereas in all ſuch caſes, where the Soldiery wanting preſent pay, are aſſigned to have Billet and Quarter found them by the ſeveral Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, it is too frequently or conſtantly practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, that ſuch Inhabitants either by want of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodations of their own for the Soldiers quartering, or by the Soldiers troubleſomneſs or difficulty to be kept quiet, and ſatisfied with ſuch Quarter as they can afford, are extremely exacted upon and enforced to give exceſſive al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowances in Money, either to Inns or Ale-houſe-keepers, where they can hire quarter for the Soldier, or elſe to the Soldier himſelf, to hire his quarter where he can; inſomuch as many are inforced to allow in ſuch caſes Sixteen pence <hi>per diem</hi> or more for a Foot Soldier, and Three ſhillings <hi>per diem</hi> or more for a Horſe and Man, to avoid the Quartering of them; and yet when the Soldiers pay comes (if they pay any thing at all towards ſatisfaction of Quarters) ſuch Inhabitants uſually receive back no more then according to the Rates heretofore allowed for diſcharging of quarters, which come far ſhort of what it uſually coſts
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:169325:4"/>
the ſaid Inhabitants: Now to prevent more ſurely the Peoples future Trouble, Damage or Oppreſſion in ſuch kinde, It is Enacted by the authority aforeſaid, That in caſe by any neglect, delay, default or accident it happen, that ſuch Forces have not their pay timely and beforehand to maintain themſelves withal, ſo as there be a neceſſity of aſſigning the Soldiers upon the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Inhabitants of the Towns or place where they lie, to have Quarter and Billet, or money in lien thereof, upon credit, until their pay do come, The Commanders of ſuch Forces ſhall not in ſuch caſe ſuffer their Soldiers or Officers to exact or take for Quarter or Billet, any more then the proportion of their days pay, and appointed allowance for additional pay, and Billet money reſpectively, for each nights and days quarter, but that the Inhabitants lend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and laying down in moneys, according to the number of Soldiers and Officers within the Quarters, for each Soldier and Non-Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioned Officer, and Officers man, the full proportion of their daily pay, according to the Eſtabliſhment for <hi>England,</hi> and of their additional pay and Billet money, allowed by the Orders and Reſolutions of Parliament for that purpoſe herewith publiſhed; and for each Commiſſion-Officer under the degree of a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptain, one half of their daily pay; and for Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptains and others above that degree, one third part of their daily pay, according to the ſaid Eſtabliſhment reſpectively, the Officers and Soldiers ſhall therewith maintain and provide themſelves both for Victuals, and all provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions for horſe and man, and alſo Billet, at ſuch Rates as they can agree upon with the Inhabitants (with reſpect to the Rules con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainted
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:169325:4"/>
in the ſaid Orders and Reſolutions) as if the ſaid Forces had received their pay before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand from the State, according to their Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignments; and the ſaid Inhabitants lending and laying down the ſaid moneys, according to the proportions aforeſaid, whileſt the ſaid Forces (continuing amongſt them) do want their pay aſſigned from the State, ſhal both be freed from any further charge or trouble for the Quarter or Billet of the ſaid Forces, according to the ſaid Orders and Reſolutions; and ſhall have the full ſum of the moneys ſo lent and laid down by them, repaid unto them without any abate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or defalkation whatſoever. And for the more ſure and orderly performance hereof, It is further Enacted, That in caſe of ſuch delay, or want of timely pay to any the ſaid Forces, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their aſſignments, the Inhabitants and Landholders within ſuch Cities, Towns, and Pariſhes, where ſuch Forces are by Order from the General, or ſuch as have authority un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him for that purpoſe, aſſigned to Quarter, ſhall according to the number of Officers and Soldiers actually preſent within the Quarters, lend and advance the moneys ſo wanting, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the proportions aforeſaid, for ſo long time as the ſaid Forces (by like Order continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there) ſhall want their pay aſſigned from the State as aforeſaid; which money the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtables or chief Civil Magiſtrates of ſuch towns and places reſpectively, are and ſhall be hereby authorized in ſuch caſe to Rate, Collect and Levy within the ſaid places, in ſuch equal way and proportions as the Forces otherwiſe would fall to be Billeted. And if any perſon refuſe to lend his ſhare, he ſhall loſe the benefit provided by this Act for thoſe that do lend the ſame; and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:169325:5"/>
the Conſtable or chief Magiſtrate, with two of the Inhabitants that agree to lend as aforeſaid, ſhall have power to aſſign ſo many ſoldiers as they think fit, to be Billeted upon the Refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers; and the money ſo lent and advanced, ſhall be paid into the hands of the reſpective Field-Officers of the Regiment, or chief Officers of the Troops or Companies quartering there, to be by them iſſued out to the Officers and Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers under them, for their pay and Billet mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney which chief Officers ſhall thereupon give to the Inhabitants their Receipt or Receipts un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their hands, for all the moneys ſo lent and advanced to them reſpectively, expreſſing for what Troops or Companies, and for what Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment the ſame is received, and promiſing and ingaging themſelves therein, fully to repay the ſame out of the next Moneys coming in unto them upon their aſſignments, from the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of the Army or otherwiſe, as pay for that time for which the moneys ſo lent do ſupply them; which the ſaid Officers ſhall accordingly do and perform, under pain of being liable them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to proceeding at Law for the ſame: And in caſe of failer, of ſuch repayment of the ſaid Money, by the ſpace of one moneth next after the lending thereof, then upon notice of ſuch failer, and producing of the ſaid Receipts before the Committee of the Army, the ſaid Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee ſhall give order to the Treaſurers at War, for the fult and ſpeedy repayment of the ſaid mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys to the ſaid Inhabitants, out of the aſſeſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the reſpective Counties and places where they live; or (if the ſame be not ſufficient) out of the aſſeſsments of the next adjacent coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; or (if that ſuffice not) then out of any mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys diſpoſable by them for ſupply of the Army;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:169325:5"/>
and ſuch order, together with the ſaid Receipts (being delivered in) ſhall be to the ſaid Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers or the Receivers in the reſpective Counties, by whom the ſaid Moneys ſhall be repaied, a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient diſcharge. And the ſaid Commanders and Officers to whom any Moneys ſhall be ſo lent (in caſe their aſſigned pay come not in time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enough) ſo as they cannot repay the ſaid mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys, before they be by order removed to other Quarters, ſhall within ten days after ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move, ſend notice to the Committee for the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, or Treaſurers at War, what moneys have been ſo lent unto them, out of what Towns or places, and in what Counties they are ſo left unpaid, under the like pain as aforeſaid. And upon theſe conſiderations, it is further Enacted, That from and after the ninth day of <hi>June,</hi> 1649. and from ſuch time before the ſaid ninth of <hi>June,</hi> as the ſaid Forces, or any of them reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively, ſhall be ſupplied with their Pay and Bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let money as aforeſaid, the ſeveral and reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Counties, places and perſons within this Commonwealth duly paying in their aſſeſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, for the Pay and Billet of the Soldiery, as by this Act, or any other Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for that purpoſe is or ſhall be required, they ſhall be wholly diſcharged and freed from all Free-quarter, Billet, or other Charge or burthen of or for the Soldiery; and all Officers and Soldiers whatſoever, having their pay and Billet money allowed as aforeſaid, ſhall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with maintain and provide for themſelves both for Victual, and other proviſions for Horſe and Man, and alſo for Lodging, and all things elſe belonging to Quarter or Billet, at ſuch Rates as they can agree for with the Inhabitants where they are or ſhall come to quarter; And no Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer or Soldier ſhall under pretence of taking
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:169325:6"/>
Quarter or Billet, enter into the Houſe of any perſon or perſons duly paying in their Aſſeſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments as aforeſaid, without his or their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent (except Inns, Taverns, Victualling-houſes and Alehouſes) nor ſhall exact or take any Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, Victual, or other proviſions for Horſe or Man, without conſent of the Owner, and due ſatisfaction given unto him for the ſame, at ſuch Rates as he ſhall agree unto, other then ſuch moneys and in ſuch caſes as is directed to be lent as aforeſaid; and otherwiſe then for ſuch neceſſary Quarter and Billet, and that in ſuch caſes onely, and according to ſuch Rules, and Terms as is expreſſed in the Rules, Reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Orders of Parliament paſſed and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed with this Act, concerning the diſpoſing and quartering of the Parliaments Forces un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the pains expreſſed in the ſaid Orders and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions.</p>
            <div type="resolutions">
               <head>ORDERS &amp; RESOLUTIONS of PARLIAMENT Concerning the diſpoſal of the preſent Forces, and Rules Concerning QUARTERING.</head>
               <opener>Reſolved and Ordered,</opener>
               <p n="1">1. THat by Saturday the ninth of <hi>June,</hi> 1649. all the Forces now in being in <hi>England,</hi> which are within the Eſtabliſhment for <hi>England,</hi> ſhall be drawn into gariſons, cities and towns, there to be ſetled in Quarters, until by due Order from the Lord General, or ſuch as have Authority under him for that purpoſe, they be removed.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That by the ſame day all the Forces now in <hi>England</hi> within the Eſtabliſhment for <hi>Ireland</hi> (except ſuch as ſhall
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:169325:6"/>
be then upon march for Tranſportation) ſhall likewiſe have quarters aſsigned in Towns or Cities (as near as may be) in order to their Tranſportation.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That all the Forces raiſed ſince the 31 of <hi>March,</hi> 1648. by any Committees or Deputy Lieutenants of particular Counties at the charge of their Counties, which are not comprehended within the Liſts of Forces to be paid as of the Eſtabliſhment for <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Ireland,</hi> lately given in from the Lord General and Councel of War; or ſhall not before the 28 day of <hi>May</hi> inſtant, 1649. be certified from the General and Councel, to be added to the ſaid liſts, ſhall be disbanded before the ſaid ninth day of <hi>June,</hi> 1649. by the Committees or Deputy Lieutenants by whom they were raiſed, and at the charge of the Counties reſpectively unleſs where the Committees ſhall ſee cauſe to keep up any of their ſaid Forces, for the particular Services of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and can finde wherewith to maintain them without Free-quarter, and without any allowance for their pay out of the Aſſeſſment of the 90000 l. <hi>per menſem;</hi> and where any ſuch County Forces are appointed to be retained in the preſent Eſtabliſhment, the Lord General is to ſignifie to the reſpective Committees or Deputy Lieutenants, what Forces of theirs are ſo retained, that the reſt may be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banded by them as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That whatever Forces lie quartered in any County, which have not been raiſed and kept up hitherto by Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion from the Lord General, or by authority of the Committees or Deputy Lieutenants of the reſpective coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and are not comprehended, in the ſaid liſts of eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for the ſervice of <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Ireland,</hi> ſhall immediately disband and diſperſe themſelves before the ſaid 28 day of <hi>May</hi> inſtant; and after that day ſhall not preſume to exact or take from any people, any Free-quarter or Free-billet, or any Money, or ought elſe in lieu of Quarter or Bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let, at their utmoſt perils, and under pain of being proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt according to Law, for what violence or wrong they ſhall do in that kinde.</p>
               <p n="5">5. That to the end all Free-billet as well as Quarter may
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:169325:7"/>
be taken off from the people, the Committee of the Army ſhall have power, and are required to make aſsignment and allowance of money in lieu of Billet to Soldiers and non-Commiſsionate Officers, in ſuch places, and to ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portions as ſhall be thought fit by the Lord General and Councel of War, and certified by the Lord General to the ſaid Committee, not exceeding the proportions of one peny <hi>per diem</hi> a man for Foot ſetled in Gariſon, two pence <hi>per diem</hi> for foot of the Army, not ſetled in Gariſon, and three pence <hi>per diem</hi> for Horſe and Dragoons, over and above their pay allowed for them by the Eſtabliſhment reſpectively; and alſo till the end of <hi>September,</hi> 1649. in regard of the preſent dearth, an additional pay not exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one peny <hi>per diem</hi> to Foot ſetled in Gariſon, two pence <hi>per diem</hi> to Foot not ſetled in Gariſon, and three pence <hi>per diem</hi> to Horſe and Dragoons; during which all lowance of additional pay, the ſaid Forces ſhall maintain themſelves with compleat Arms, without any charge to the State: And for performance thereof, the chief Officer in each Troop and Company, ſhall have power to ſtop the ſaid additional pay from ſuch as are defective, until they do compleat their Arms.</p>
               <p n="6">6. That from and after the ſaid ninth day of <hi>June,</hi> the ſeveral and reſpective counties, places and perſons within this Commonwealth, duly paying in their aſſeſſments, for the pay and billet of the Soldiery, as by any Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament for that purpoſe is or ſhall be required, they ſhall be wholly diſcharged and freed from all Free quarter, Free billet, or other charge or burthen of or for the Soldiery: And all Officers and Soldiers whatſoever, having their pay and billet Money allowed as aforeſaid, ſhall therewith maintain and provide themſelves, both for victual and other proviſions for Horſe and Man, and alſo for lodging and all things belonging to Quarter or Billet, at ſuch rate, as they can agree for with the Inhabitants where they are, or ſhall come to quarter; and no Officer or Soldier ſhall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pretence of taking quarter or billet, enter into the houſe of any perſon or perſons, duly paying in their Aſſeſſments
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:169325:7"/>
as aforeſaid, without his or their conſent, except Inns, Taverns, Victualling houſes or Alehouſes, nor ſhall exact or take any money, victuals, or other proviſions for horſe or man, without conſent of the Owner, and due ſatisfaction given him for the ſame at ſuch rates as he ſhall agree unto, other then ſuch mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, &amp; in ſuch caſe as is directed to be lent in the Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment herewith publiſhed; and otherwiſe then for ſuch neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry quarter and billet, and that in ſuch caſes onely, and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſuch Rules and Terms as is hereafter expreſſed; <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That whenſoever any Forces ſhall by vertue of Order from the General, or from ſuch as ſhall have authority under him for that purpoſe, be upon a march or removing quarters, they ſhall at the Towns or Pariſhes where they ſhall be ordered to quarter, be billetted in the uſual way by their Quartermaſters or Superior Officers reſpectively, according to the Aſsignment or Directions of the Conſtables or chief Civil Magiſtrate in the ſaid Towns or Pariſhes; or in caſe of their refuſal or neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect to make aſsignment or direction therein, then at the dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Quartermaſter or Superior Officer, and the reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive inhabitants where any Officers or Soldiers ſhall be ſo billetted as aforeſaid, ſhall receive them to quarter and Billet accordingly, and for one night or two at the moſt, ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide lodging and neceſſary billet, finde them victual, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their ordinary Family-diet (wherewith the Soldier ſhall be contented) and alſo hay, or in Summer time graſs for their horſes, for which the Soldiery ſhall pay at the rate of eight pence <hi>per diem</hi> for a Foot Soldier, twelve pence <hi>per diem</hi> for a Dragooner, &amp; fifteen pence <hi>per diem</hi> for a Trooper and his horſe, and for what Provender they uſe, as they can agree; and the like for non-Commiſsionate Officers, and Commiſsion Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers men, of foot, horſe or dragoons reſpectively, and Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion Officers ſhall pay as they can agree, not exceeding one third part of their daily pay reſpectively, beſide for Proven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der as they can agree: and after the firſt two nights (if they ſtay longer) both Officers and Soldiers ſhall with their pay maintain and finde themſelves as aforeſaid, and pay for what they have, at ſuch Rates as they can agree with the Inhabitants, both for victual, and other proviſion for Horſe and Man, but
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:169325:8"/>
for the next five nights after the ſaid two nights (if they ſtay there ſo long) both the Soldiers and Officers, if they ſhall not otherwiſe agree with the Inhabitants ſooner for their Billet, <hi>viz.</hi> Lodging, Stable room, and the uſe of their ordinary fire and candlelight, ſhall have the ſame found for that ſpace by the reſpective Inhabitants where they ſhall be ſo Billeted as aforeſaid, paying ſuch Inhabitants for the ſame according to the rates allowed to the Soldiery reſpectively, in lieu of Billet as aforeſaid; And after the ſaid five nights (if they be to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue at or or about the ſame Towns longer) then both Officers and Soldiers ſhall thenceforth finde and provide themſelves Billet alſo for their Money, where they can obtain and agree for the ſame, either in the ſaid Towns or Pariſhes, or at any other Village or place adjacent, within ſuch diſtance as the chief Officer commanding in the Quarter ſhall allow of; and ſhall not after the ſaid five nights, under pretence of Quarter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or Billet, enter into, or continue in the houſe of any the ſaid Inhabitants (duly paying in their Aſſeſſments as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid) without his or their conſent, except Inns, Taverns, Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctualling-houſes or Alehouſes, nor ſhall exact or take any Moneys, Victuals, or other Proviſions for Horſe or Man, without the owners conſent and ſatisfaction for the ſame, at ſuch rates as he ſhall agree unto.</p>
               <p>Provided, That the Conſtables or chief Magiſtrates in the ſaid reſpective Towns and Places, ſhall cauſe the Inhabitants to afford the Soldiery ſuch proviſions for horſe and men as they have to ſpare, at ſuch Market price as they uſually ſold the ſame for unto others, within a week before the Forces came firſt to quarter there, and for that purpoſe, the reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Civil Magiſtrates, or (upon his or their refuſal) ſuch chief Officer as aforeſaid, ſhall in ſuch caſe have and exerciſe the ſame power and authority, for the rating of proviſions for neceſſary ſupply of the Soldiery, as by Law any Magiſtrate hath or may exerciſe, for the bringing forth or rating of Corn for ſupply of the poor, in caſe of engroſsing or foreſtalling in time of dearth.</p>
               <p>Provided alſo, That in all places to which any Forces come to quarter as aforeſaid, where there is lodging, receipt, and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:169325:8"/>
ſufficient for the number of men and horſe, at Inns, Taverns, Victualling-houſes or Alehouſes, the ſaid Forces, or ſo many of them as there is ſuch receipt and lodging for, ſhall after the two nights of their ſtay, be diſpoſed of for billet into ſuch Inns Taverns, Victualling-houſes and Alehouſes, unleſs they can agree for their billet at other places within the quarter, or ſuch diſtance therefrom as aforeſaid; and in ſuch caſe ſhall not after the ſaid firſt two nights, under pretence of quartering or billet, enter into, or continue in the houſe of any other In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitant, duly paying in his Aſſeſſments as aforeſaid, without his own conſent: And where ever any Soldiers or Officers ſhall come to quarter in any Inn, Tavern, Victualling-houſe or Alehouſe, without conſent of the Inhabitant, they ſhall accept and be content with ſuch ſufficient lodging, and ſuch convenient ſtable-room, as the Inhabitant hath and ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point for them, and ſhall pay the Inhabitant for the ſame, at the ſame rate as is allowed to them by the State for billet as aforeſaid reſpectively, unleſs they ſhall by agreement with the Inhabitant, have with him their diet or Horſemeat as other Gueſts, or at ſuch rates as he ſhall agree to take; and alſo provided, that in caſe the Forces want their pay aſsigned from the State, they ſhall be ſupplied with money by way of Loan, from the Inhabitants of the Towns and Places with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in their quarters, according to the Act of Parliament herewith publiſhed.</p>
               <p>And theſe Rules are to hold as well upon the drawing of the Forces into Cities or Towns, by or before the ſaid Ninth of <hi>June,</hi> according to the Reſolutions aforegoing, as upon any remove or change of quarters afterwards by due Order as aforeſaid, and ſhall be duly and conſtantly obſerved and kept by and betwixt all Officers and Soldiers under pay and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the Parliament in this Nation; and all Inhabitants of ſuch places within this Commonwealth, where any the ſaid Forces ſhall happen to quarter by due Order as aforeſaid, while Aſſeſſments for the Army continue to be paid, unleſs actual War by Invaſion, Inſurrection or Rebellion within the Land ſhall happen ſo to hinder the due levying of Aſſeſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and neceſsitate ſuch encreaſe of Forces, as that the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:169325:9"/>
Soldiery cannot be conſtantly paid as is intended: And all Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary Officers for thoſe under their reſpective Commands, and all Civil Magiſtrates for thoſe under their reſpective Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, are required ſtrictly to ſee to, and to take order for the due obſervance of theſe Rules and Directions aforegoing; and if any Officer or Soldier ſhall offend, contrary to the effect of the premiſes, upon complaint and proof thereof made before the Colonel, or other Field-Officer of the Regiment, or before the chief Officer commanding in the quarters, every ſuch Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendor ſhall be caſhiered out of the Army and Service of the Parliament; and for any damage done to any Countreyman, contrary to the premiſes, ſhall be awarded and compelled to give full ſatisfaction out of his pay; and for ſuch damage (if he give not ſuch ſatisfaction) ſhall be left to the Law; and for any violence contrary to the effect of the premiſes (if it be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pital or criminal) being firſt caſhiered as aforeſaid, ſhall by the ſaid chief Officer be ſent and delivered over to the next Juſtice of the Peace, to be dealt with, and proceeded againſt for the ſame, according to Law; and if the ſaid chief Officer ſhall fail of his duty, in not puniſhing and proceeding againſt ſuch Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendors as is aforeſaid, he ſhall be caſhiered, and be lyable to make ſatisfaction himſelf; and if any Countreyman ſhall wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and obſtinately offend, to the prejudice of the Soldier, contrary to the effect of the premiſes, he ſhall loſe the benefit of that exemption from Free-quarter and Free-billet, which is hereby provided for.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <signed>Hen: Scobel, Cleric. Parliamenti.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
